--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.tv
影片压制：死亡骑士　调校：阿凡提　招募Q号：324446465
天才少女
歌曲
--------
The Wind
数学思想：黛安阿德勒会是最终解决
纳维尔-斯托克斯方程的人吗？
著名数学家自杀身亡
其弟弟弗兰克在世
歌曲
----
Pretty Bird
对纳维尔-斯托克斯方程的证明
喂 快点
Hey! Come on. Let's move!
不
No!
- 让我看看 - 不
- Let me see. - No!
快点 我给你做了特别的早餐
Come on. I made you a special breakfast.
你不会做饭
You can't cook.
喂 玛丽 开门
Hey, Mary, open up!
你真漂亮
You look beautiful.
我看起来像个卡通人物
I look like a Disney character.
哪儿特别了
Where's the "special"?
什么
The what?
你说给我做了特别的早餐
You said you made me a special breakfast.
请别逼我上学
Please don't make me go.
你可以继续在家教我
You can keep homeschooling me.
我知道的都教给你了
I've taught you everything I know.
可我不想上学
But I don't wanna go.
我还不想上班呢 但我还是得去
Well, I don't wanna go to work, but I do.
你不上班的 你只是在码头修船
You don't go to work. You fix the boats on a dock.
好吧 这个例子不恰当 但你还是要上学
Okay. It's a poor example, but you're still going.
弗雷德怎么办
But what about Fred?
它怎么了
What about him?
你不会照顾它
You won't take care of him.
你不喜欢猫
You don't like cats.
我不喜欢两只眼的猫
I don't like two-eyed cats.
但弗雷德是一只眼
Fred, as you know, is monocular.
谁来给它抛球
Who's gonna throw him his ping pong ball?
弗雷德不会有事的 别再争论了
Fred's gonna be fine. No more argument, okay?
这事讨论的没完没了
We've discussed this ad nauseam.
没完没了是什么意思
What's ad nauseam?
这个词都不会?
Oh, you don't know?
那你需要上学了
Well, looks like someone needs school.
会很开心的
This is gonna be fun.
你今天会结识新同学
You're gonna meet kids today
一辈子都可以跟他们借钱花
you can borrow money from the rest of your life.
去吧
Come on.
你会做得很好的
You're gonna be great.
你只需要
You know, just...
尽量跟别的孩子一样
I don't know. Try bein' a kid.
弗兰克
Frank!
弗兰克 我知道你能听到
Frank, I know you hear me.
弗兰克
Frank!
你现在补救还来得及
There's still time for you to undo this nonsense.
开车去把孩子接回来
Go get in your car and go get that child.
我允许你可以
Are you technically allowed to
随时用这钥匙了吗
use those keys whenever you want?
你怎么能
How can you stand there...
这么淡定
acting all calm and everything, Frank,
对此毫不在乎呢
and make light of this?
去把她接回来 趁现在还来得及
Now go get her back before it's too late.
她得去外面的世界
She gotta get out in the world.
她没有同龄的朋友
She has no friends her age.
没有社交技能
No social skills.
不知道该怎么做个孩子
She doesn't know how to be a kid.
前天晚上 她对我说
Two nights ago, she told me
即使德国脱欧
that even if Germany bails out the euro...
还是有可能发生全球经济衰退
there could still be a worldwide depression.
我盯着天花板三个小时
I was staring at the ceiling for three hours.
我很担心
I'm so worried.
别这样 罗伯特
Come on, Roberta.
你要是哭
If you start crying,
我就只能装哭了
I'm gonna have to pretend to start crying.
喂
Hey.
有些事是可以不在乎的
You know, there's something you could be overlookin'.
她没事的
This could work out.
可能吧
Maybe.
但如果她被谁带走了
But if anybody takes that baby away...
我会让你死在睡梦里
I'll smother you in your sleep.
早上好 弗雷德
Morning, Fred
1加1等于2
One plus one is two.
这是今天的第一课
That is fact number one of today.
谁知道2加2等于几
Who can tell me what two plus two is?
谁知道
Who's got it?
等于4
Four.
很好 唐娜
Excellent, Donna.
正确 2加2的确等于4
It is. Two plus two is, indeed, four.
好 谁想试试回答3加3等于几
Okay, who wants to try three plus three?
3加3 我没听错吧
Three plus three? Really?
你说什么
I beg your pardon?
这算哪门子学校
What kind of school is this anyway?
这是那种
It's the kind of school
学生不能在课堂上随便说话的学校
where students don't speak without permission.
好吧 傻子都知道等于6
All right. But everyone knows it's six.
需要被老师点到名
Nobody in this classroom speaks...
才可以说话
unless they are called upon.
好吗 大家都知道了吗
Okay? Is everybody clear on that?
是 老师
Yes, ma'am.
好的 玛丽 请你站起来
Good. Mary, can you stand up please?
站起来 站起来 孩子
Stand on up. Stand up, babe.
我给你出几个题 既然你这么聪明
These questions are for you because you're so advanced.
9加8等于几
What is nine plus eight?
等于17
17.
是的 正确 很好
Yeah. Yes, it is. That's good.
那么
What is...
15加17呢
15 plus 17?
等于32
32.
对 回答正确
Yeah. That is right.
那好
All right, then.
那么57加135等于多少
Well, what is 57 plus 135?
等于192
192.
对
Yeah.
那么如果
Can you tell me...
57和135相乘呢
what 57 multiplied by 135 is?
好
Okay.
谁知道4…
Who can tell me what four...
等于7695
7,695.
这个没人会吧
I don't think anyone can do that.
平方根是87.7
The square root is 87.7.
和一些小数
And change.
没完没了是什么意思
Now what does ad nauseam mean?
我班上有个奇怪的学生
I have a very strange kid.
我有27个奇怪的学生呢
I have 27 strange kids.
早上好
Good morning.
很好 同学们 去座位上坐下
That's great, guys, but take your seats, okay?
天啊 再见
Oh, God. See ya.
早上好 史蒂文森老师
Good morning, Ms. Stevenson.
早上好
Good morning.
我能旁听吗
Mind if I sit in?
当然可以
Not at all!
好了 同学们
Okay, class.
有件好事告诉大家
I have a treat for you.
我来介绍一下戴维斯校长
I would like to introduce you to our principal, Mrs. Davis.
早上好 一年级的同学们
Good morning, first graders.
早上好 戴维斯校长
Good morning, Mrs. Davis.
你们准备好开始这美好的一学年了吗
Are you ready for a great year?
是的
Yes!
怎么了 玛丽
Uh... Yes, Mary?
她是学校的老大?
She's the boss?
戴维斯夫人是我们的校长 好了
Mrs. Davis is our principal. Okay...
那我要你
Okay. Now I want you
给弗兰克打电话
to get on your phone and call Frank...
让他来接我走
and tell him to get me out of here!
慢着 他是她爸爸 我认识他
Wait a minute.That's the dad? I know him.
我每周五晚都能在酒吧看到他
I see him at Ferg's almost every Friday night.
他是个内向 忧郁的帅哥
He's the quiet, damaged hot guy.
你每周五晚去酒吧干什么
What are you doing at Ferg's every Friday night?
勾搭他啊
Trying to get picked up by him.
等一下 你好
Excuse me? Hi.
是我老师
Oh. Look, it's my teacher.
可能是想问我1加1等于几
Probably wants to remind mewhat one plus one is.
你到车上去
Go to the car, okay?
- 你好 - 你好
- Hi.- Hi.
对不起冲你喊还追出来
Sorry to yell at you and then chase you down.
没关系 你是玛丽的老师?
It's okay. Mary's teacher?
是的 我叫邦妮史蒂文森
Yes. I'm Bonnie Stevenson.
我叫弗兰克 你好 今天的事很抱歉
Frank. How are you? Sorry about today.
她有点兴奋过头
I know she got a little overexcited.
可能因为第一天上学吧
I think it's just first day jitters.
是啊
Sure. Yeah.
我们有点晚了 我们该走了
We're running a little late actually. We gotta get going.
我想说的不是那事
Okay. I don't even wanna talk about that.
- 我只耽误你一会 - 好的
- I'll keep you just a minute.- Okay.
我觉得你女儿
I think your daughter...
我觉得玛丽可能是天才
I think Mary might be gifted.
什么
What?
今天在数学课上 她回答了一些非常难的
Yeah. Today in Math, she answered some really...
- 不 不 - 请听我说
- Oh, no, no, no. That's... - No, please.
- 那不是天才 - 非常难的问题
- It's not gifted.- Really difficult questions.
好
All right.
一个7岁的孩子
Just that a seven-year-old would...
这是特拉亨伯格
It's Trachtenberg.
- 特拉亨伯格速算法 - 什么
- Jakow Trachtenberg.- I'm sorry?
他在纳粹集中营里待了7年
Spent seven years in a Nazi concentration camp.
发明了一种速算系统
Developed a system to rapidly solve problems.
叫做特拉亨伯格方法
It's the Trachtenberg method.
可她
But she's...
她毕竟才7岁
I mean, she's seven though.
我8岁时候就学会了
I learned it when I was eight.
看我像天才吗
Do I look gifted to you?
自从发明了计算器
It's kind of gone out of vogue
这种方法就过时了 不过
since the invention of the calculator...
我在酒吧里还是能够靠它赢酒喝
but, uh, I can still win a drink at a bar using it.
今天的事很抱歉
Sorry for today.
- 她不会再犯了 - 好
- Won't happen again.- Okay.
很高兴认识你 邦妮
Nice to meet you. Bonnie.
弗兰克
Frank.
我要说明 我本来就不想
For the record, I didn't wanna go
上那个破学校
to the stupid school in the first place.
我后排的男生
And the boy in the next row
行为不检点 没个孩子样
acts inappropriately for someone who's a child.
抱歉 我还是要无视你
I'm sorry. I'm still passive aggressively ignoring you.
别的同学也回答问题了 没受处分啊
Other kids answer questions.They don't get into trouble.
你受处分不是因为回答问题
You didn't get in trouble for answering questions.
是因为冲校长发脾气
You yelled at the principal.
知道吗 你会觉得这个有意思
You know what? You're gonna find this interesting.
我搜索了一下 一年级学生冲校长发脾气
So, I googled "first graders who yell at the principal..."
你绝对想不到
and statistically,you're never gonna
有多少学生这么干过
believe how many kids do it.
有多少
How many?
0个
None.
弗兰克 我很抱歉 真的
Frank, I'm sorry. I'm really sorry.
得了吧
Yeah, right.
你在学校里不能那么炫耀
You can't show off like that at school.
我知道
I know.
你保证过不会 但你第一天就…
You promised you wouldn't, then the first day...
我知道 是我的不对
I know, I know. I screwed up.
你觉得这条船需要试航吗
Do you think maybe this boat needs a test ride?
去把弗雷德抱来
Go get Fred.
不要跑
Don't run.
我聆听风的声音 越过我灵魂的风声
∮ I listen to the wind To the wind of my soul ∮
我将会在哪里停下我的脚步 我想
∮ Where I'll end up Well, I think ∮
只有上帝才知道吧
∮ Only God really knows ∮
我曾坐在烈日下
∮ I've sat upon the setting sun ∮
但是我从未 从未
∮ But never, never, never, never ∮
渴望过水源
∮ I never wanted water once ∮
不我从未那样过
∮ No, never, never, never ∮
弗雷德很喜欢看矶鹬
Fred loves to watch the sandpipers.
它想去抓一只
He thinks he'd like to catch one...
但它会后悔的
but he'd regret it.
弗雷德不杀小动物
Fred's not a killer.
它有爱心
He's a lover.
妈妈会希望我上这学校吗
Would my mom have wanted me to go to this school?
我说不好
I can only guess.
但我跟你说
But I'll tell you what,
她肯定希望你交些朋友
she would have wanted you to have friends.
傻瓜朋友吗
Idiot friends?
她还会希望你对人有同情心
And she'd want you to have compassion for others.
就像猫对矶鹬那样
Like a cat can have for a sandpiper.
如果同学们不喜欢我呢
But what if they don't like me?
那他们是傻瓜
Then they're idiots.
早上好 同学们
Good morning, class.
早上好 史蒂文森老师
Good morning, Ms. Stevenson.
早上好 玛丽
Good morning, Mary.
早上好 史蒂文森老师
Good morning, Ms. Stevenson.
好 早上好
Okay, good morning.
你规矩点
Get a hold of yourself.
我展示和讲述的内容
For my Show and Tell,I have...
是一只特别棒的猫
the most awesome cat in the history of time.
它不光名字叫弗雷德 而且
Not only is his name Fred, but...
它只有一只眼
He has just one eye.
一只眼 不信数数看
Uno. Go ahead and count...
反正数来数去就是一只
but I promise you, it's always one.
它怎么失去一只眼的
How did he lose his eye?
不知道 我当时不在
I don't know. I wasn't there.
我是在一个垃圾桶旁边捡到它的
Just found him inside of a trash can
在一瓶酒旁边
next to a bottle of alcohol or something.
它是一只聪明的猫 但没人发现这一点
He is a smart, smart cat, but no one realizes that.
没人能理解它 没人
No one understands him. No one.
把名字写在试卷上方
Put your name on the top of the paper...
我就知道是谁回答的这么好了
so that I know who did such good work.
我给你我的笔
I left my pen with you.
把试卷传递一下
Pass those around, guys.
好吗 我想看看你们的解答
Okay? I wanna see your work.
转过身去 面对课桌
Turn around, face the desk.
考虑一下答案是怎么得出来的
Think about how you get to the answer.
不要只是猜
It's not just about, you know, guessing.
试卷要整洁
Don't be messy.
做完了
Done.
我看看
Let's see.
嗯
Mmm-hmm.
我估计你会很快做完
Okay. I thought you might finish quickly,
所以给你加了一些题
so a little something extra.
做完了
Done.
啊
Oh...
你知道我是谁吗
Do you know who I am?
嗨 玛丽的老师
Hey! Mary's teacher...
邦妮
Bonnie.
你对我撒了谎
You lied to me.
好吧
Okay.
你能具体些吗
Can you narrow it down?
我想了解我的学生玛丽的真相
I'd like to know the truth about Mary, my student...
你的外甥女
your niece.
我当时
I was running
赶着去约会
ridiculously late for a date...
我姐姐带着玛丽来了
and my sister showed up with Mary.
她从来不会不请自来
And she never just showed up unannounced.
从未带孩子来过
She never showed up with the baby.
她说她想聊聊
She said she wanted to talk.
她说她也需要聊聊
She said she needed to talk.
我说等我回来后再谈
I told her I would talk to her when I got back.
我想着如果约会晚了那么久
I think I figured showing up that late to my date...
滚床单的机会就不大了
would hurt my chances of gettin' laid.
那晚回来时 玛丽在沙发上
Came home that night and Mary was on the couch...
而戴安死在了卫生间地板上
and found Diane on the bathroom floor.
我完全没料到她会…
I mean, there's no way I could known...
但我本该料到的
but I should known.
六年半后
Six and a half years later,
我还是和玛丽在一起
me and Mary are still hangin' out.
那她父亲呢
And what about the father?
黛安不善交际
Diane was so socially awkward...
不善辨别好男人和坏男人
she didn't date enough to know a good guy from a bad guy.
他们交往一个月就分手了
This particular guy didn't last a month.
没有外祖父母吗
And no grandparents?
我爸在我8岁时去世 我妈…
Dad died when I was eight. My mom...
简单的说 在黛安怀孕后
Short version is she turned her back on Diane
她就不管她了
when she got pregnant.
为什么
Why?
不符合她的计划
Didn't fit into her plan.
我妈是个很严格的人
She's an exacting woman, my mother.
不妥协
Uncompromising.
典型的英国人
Very British.
是举止很英式 还是…
Do you mean, British in demeanor or...
- 不 她就是… - 是英国人
- No. Like she's... - She's from England.
英国人 对
From England. Yeah.
那么玛丽确实是天才喽?
So, Mary is a genius?
啊
Oh!
当心 当心
Look out. Look out.
你的小动物们要跑了 笨蛋
Your little animals are escaping, dumbass.
喂 你不该笑的
Hey! You should not be laughing!
你欺负小孩子
You did a mean thing to a little kid!
你能把我怎么样
What are you gonna do about it?
喂 你没事吧
Hey. Hey, you okay?
没事吧 好
You good? All right.
这事怎么解决
How do we resolve this?
她够被开除了
You know, she could be expelled.
天啊 希望不要开除
God. I hope not.
但如果别的学生第一次违纪就被开除
But if every other first-time offender was expelled,
那么就这么办
I guess fair is fair.
你能不能认真点
Are you gonna take this seriously?
好的 只要你实实在在的 我也实实在在的
Sure. You don't bluff me, I don't bluff you.
史蒂文森老师说
Ms. Stevenson believes
你的孩子很超常
that your child is exceptional...
我们的课程对她来说
and has talents that our curriculum
完全没有挑战性
can't begin to challenge.
我恰巧
It just so happens
有位好朋友
that I am good friends with the headmaster
是橡树天才教育学院的校长
of the Oaks Academy for Gifted Education.
他经常说
He has always said
如果我能碰到万里挑一的神童
that if I find that one in a million...
那种万里挑一的学费要三万美元呢
And the one in a million has a $30,000 tuition.
阿德勒先生 我可以为你女儿申请奖学金
Mr. Adler, I can get your daughter a scholarship.
全额的
Full ride.
我有把握才说这个话
I wouldn't say it if I couldn't do it.
我知道把这女孩送到那种学校
I realize, putting that girl in that setting,
是你们最通常的做法
you know, 99 times out of a 100, that's what you do.
那可是橡树学校 是一流的学校
It's the Oaks. It's a great school.
我搜索过
I looked into it.
但我们家族有好几人去过这种学校
But this family has a history with those schools.
我觉得她最不需要的
And I think the last thing that little girl needs
就是强化她的与众不同感
is reinforcement that she's different.
相信我 她有这感觉 所以
Trust me, she knows. So...
我觉得玛丽必须留在这学校
I think Mary, I think she's gotta be here.
今天的事不好 动手打人是不对的
Today's a bad ending. You can't hit people.
但一个12岁的男生欺负一个7岁男生
But a 12-year-old bullies a seven- year- old
她能挺身而出
and she stands up?
她这么做你知道我有多欣慰吗
Do you know how important it is to me that she did that?
知道我有多骄傲吗 你们难道不是吗
You know how proud I am of her? Aren't you?
阿德勒先生 你女儿把一个男生打得…
Mr. Adler, your daughter shattered a young boy's...
我知道 打人是不对的
I know. You can't hit people.
我会跟她明确这一点 这我懂
That will be made very clear. I get that.
但如果把未来的领导人和普通人分开
But Mrs. Davis, if we separate our leaders,
让他们脱离我们这样的群众
if we segregate them from people like you and me,
他们就会成为政客
you get congressmen.
所以我很抱歉
So, I'm sorry.
我也很想接受你的提议 但我不能
I wish I could take your offer, but Mary stays.
除非你把她开除
Unless you kick her out.
这是错误的 我们无法给她提供
This is a mistake. We'll never be able to raise this child
她所需要的教育水平
to the level of scholarship she deserves.
让她降低到普通人的水平就行了
Well, just dumb her down into a decent human being.
这样都满意
Everybody wins.
我先离开一下
You know what? Can you excuse me one minute?
把她所有的档案材料
Bring me every piece of paperwork
拿给我
we have on this girl.
喂
Hey.
你觉得这么做真的好吗
Are you sure you know what you're doing?
不知道
No.
好了 玛丽
Okay. Mary, I think
你是不是有话要对同学们说
you have something you'd like to say to the class.
你上台来说吧
You wanna hop up and say it?
好吧 我该说点什么
Okay. I'm supposed to say something.
打人是不对的 即使打的是坏人
Hitting people is wrong even if they're bad.
我不会再打人了 所以不用怕我
I won't do it again, so don't be afraid of me.
好 谢谢你
Okay. Thank you.
我能说句真心话吗
Now can I say something I wanna say?
好的
Sure.
在摔坏之前
Before they ruined it,
贾斯汀做的动物园是最棒的
Justin's zoo was the best art project.
暂时没人超过 做得特别棒
By far. It was awesome.
来吧 用力鼓掌
Come on. A little harder.
好的
Okay.
谢谢 谢谢
Thank you. Thank you.
有个女人站在我们家门前
There's a lady standing in front of our door.
是谁啊
Who is it?
我哪知道 我才7岁
How should I know? I'm seven.
她是你外婆
That would be your grandmother.
我嘞个去
Holy shit!
苹果 哇
An Apple? Whoa.
是个苹果笔记本电脑 孩子
It's a MacBook, darling.
是最先进的 有视网膜显示屏
Top of the line with the Retina Display.
你知道谁也有视网膜显示屏吗
Hey, you know who else has a Retina Display?
弗雷德
Fred!
玛丽 我听说你喜欢数学
Mary, I understand you like mathematics.
所以在这电脑里
So, on there,
你能找到一本
you'll find a great
查尔斯奇默写的绝版书
out-of-print book by Charles Zimmer
名叫 高等代数的演变
called Transitions in Advanced Algebra.
是啊 我喜欢那本书
Yeah. Love that book.
你是说你看过
You're saying you've read it?
看过 我已经转向研究微分方程了
Yeah. I've kind of moved on to differential equations now.
要注意礼貌 谢谢你外婆
Don't forget your manners. Thank your grandma.
谢谢你 外婆
Thank you, Grandma.
叫我外婆或伊芙琳都可以
Grandmother or Evelyn will do just fine.
里面远不止这本书
There's so much more on there.
你肯定能找到有难度的
Things I know you'll find really challenging.
是的 但可惜她明天还要上学
Yes. But sadly, it's a school night
今晚要做作业
and there's homework to do.
真是个意外的惊喜
What a surprise though, right?
跟你外婆或伊芙琳道别吧
Say good night to Grandmother or Evelyn.
再见
Good night.
我现在特想吃药
I'd kill a priest for a Benadryl.
还是过敏吗
Still with the allergies?
你干嘛养猫
Why in God's name have you got a cat?
你又不喜欢猫
You don't even like cats.
不是我的猫 是玛丽的猫
It's not my cat. It's Mary's cat.
我只是搭顺风车
I'm just along for the ride.
我来猜猜
So let me guess.
是戴维斯校长请你来的吧
Our lovely principal, Ms. Davis.
千万别得罪
Never get on the bad side of small-minded people
有点实权的小人
who have a little authority.
我记得教过你这一点
I thought I taught you that.
你来干什么
What are you doin' here?
难道我没权利
You don't think I have the right
来看望我外孙女吗
to see my granddaughter?
你有 我很欣慰你历尽千辛万苦
I do. I'm thrilled your seven-year exhaustive search
终于在七年后找到了外孙女
has finally come to a fruitful conclusion.
我觉得现在说话不方便
I don't think this is an appropriate time to talk.
至少这里不方便
Certainly not the setting.
等你回来的时候 一只这么大的蟑螂
While I was waiting, a cockroach this big
想偷走我的鞋
tried to steal my shoe.
是啊 它们会偷鞋
Yeah. They'll take a shoe.
说真的 就这里吗
Honestly, this?
住在这荒凉的蚊子农场是理性的选择吗
This godforsaken mosquito ranch was a conscious choice?
我可以开车送你去机场
I could drop you back off at the airport.
这里面好多很棒的数学题
This thing is loaded with cool problems.
你在任教吗
So, are you teaching?
我是修船的
I repair boats.
- 别胡说 - 我手艺还不赖
- Please. - I'm not bad at it either.
难怪你皮肤粗糙
Well, then, that explains this.
这里不卖防晒霜吗
They don't sell sunscreen here?
我擦了防晒霜
I wear sunscreen.
擦得不够 你还要戴上帽子
Not enough. And you need a hat.
能让脸和脖子不被晒的大帽子
A big hat that shades your face and neck.
不能拿自己的皮肤开玩笑
You're playing Russian roulette with your skin.
你跟个A片制片人似的
You look like a porn producer.
好的 我谢谢你的建议
Okay. I appreciate the advice. I do.
但我们不是来谈防晒霜的吧
But we're not here to talk about sunscreen, are we?
闲聊几句也不行吗 那太遗憾了
Oh, so no more small talk? That's a shame.
好吧 你为那孩子创造的环境
Okay. The environment you have created for that child
她的住处 她上的学校
where she lives, the school she attends,
都是配不上她的
it's substandard, every bit of it.
我不赞同
I disagree.
我们要互相坦诚
We're getting nowhere
否则根本谈不出什么结果来
if we're not gonna be honest with each other.
我没不坦诚
I am being honest.
好吧 不带走她 我是不会走的
I see. Fine. Well, I'm not leaving without her.
那你就住在佛罗里达吧
Well, welcome to Florida.
弗兰克 请你理智一点
Frank, please listen to reason.
总有一天 你要么自己想明白了
At some point, either you're gonna come to the conclusion,
要么法院会派人
or someone in authority
跟你逐字逐句的讲明白
is going to spell it out for you
这孩子的利益才是最重要的
that the child's best interest is all that matters.
既然你不客气 我也跟你直说了
You're gonna make me pull rank, I will.
黛安不想把她交给你
Diane didn't want you to have her.
黛安
Diane...
黛安考虑事情不够周全
Diane didn't always think things through.
她可是世上最聪明的人之一
Arguably one of the brightest minds on the planet.
可这为她带来了什么呢
Good luck going down that road.
如果她看到
And what do you think she'd say
孩子住在这种地方 她会怎么说
if she saw how her child is living now?
你真以为她会满意吗
Do you honestly think she'd be pleased?
看着孩子过着平常的生活 她当然满意
That she's living a somewhat normal life? Yes. I do.
她不是平常的孩子 把她当成平常的孩子
She's not normal. And treating her as such...
是你的重大过失
is negligence on a grand scale.
我知道你是出于好心
I know your heart's in the right place on this.
但你这是耽误了她的潜力
But you are denying the girl her potential. You are.
我可以提供给她 我可以丰富她的人生
I can provide for her, I can enrich her life.
得了吧 伊芙琳 你要把她带走
Oh, come on, Evelyn. You're gonna take that girl,
让她上无数的学习班
you're gonna bury her in tutors...
然后让她去某个研究机构工作
then you're gonna loan her out to some think tank...
让她一辈子
where she can talk non-trivial zeros...
跟一群俄国老头子谈论非平凡零点
with a bunch of old Russian guys for the rest of her life.
而你会埋没她
And you'd bury her under a rock.
你不明白要成为伟人
Look, I don't expect you to understand
都是要付出代价的
the price you have to pay for greatness.
我明白 否则玛丽也就不会归我抚养了
Oh, I do. That's why I have Mary in the first place.
没必要说这种话吧
That's uncalled for.
你姐姐有很多问题
Your sister had a laundry list of problems.
她本来有希望解决纳维尔-斯托克斯方程
She could have solved Navier-Stokes
青史留名
and gone down in history...
成为史上最伟大的数学家之一
as one of the greatest mathematicians of all time.
可她没有 因为她没能做下去
But she didn't because she couldn't finish.
她软弱
She was weak.
像她的父亲那样 像她的…
Weak like her father and weak like...
好吧
Well...
如果你说的是我
Now, if it's who I think it is...
这顿饭就吃的没什么滋味了
Kinda puts a black cloud over our luncheon.
你还是那么倔强 怀恨在心
You're still stubborn and vindictive.
这种话别随便说
Careful, Mother.
俗话说有其母必有其子
There's an apple and tree analogy lurking.
你们可以点菜了吗
You guys ready to order?
我有个提议
Here's an idea.
别再考虑你和我
Stop thinking about me and you...
考虑一下怎么样才对孩子最好吧
and start thinking about what's best for the child.
对任何理性的人来说 答案都是明显的
For any reasonable person, a clear picture will emerge.
如果不是 我建议你打电话给律师
If it doesn't, I suggest you call your attorney.
他会喝上一桶啤酒
He'll have the bucket of beer.
我们到外面玩玩吧
Hey, let's go outside.
不
No.
拜托 外面多好玩啊
Come on. It's nice out.
我没兴趣
I don't care.
喂 今天别再看数学了
Hey, no more math today.
上帝存在吗
Is there a God?
不知道
I don't know.
你就告诉我
Just tell me.
知道的话我会告诉你的
I would if I could.
可我不知道 没人知道
But I don't know. And neither does anybody else.
罗伯塔知道
Roberta knows.
不 罗伯塔那是信仰
No. Roberta has faith
这是好事
and that's a great thing to have.
但信仰归信仰
But faith's about what you think, feel.
不等于知道
Not what you know.
那么耶稣呢
What about Jesus?
他是好人 要听他的教诲
Love that guy. Do what he says.
可他是上帝吗
But is he God?
不知道
I don't know.
我虽然有观点
I have an opinion.
但只是我个人观点 不一定对
But that's my opinion. I could be wrong.
所以不能误导你
So why would I screw up yours?
可以自己考虑
Use your head.
但也可以盲目的信仰
But don't be afraid to believe in things either.
电视上有个人说
Huh. There was a guy on TV
上帝并不存在
who said there was no God.
那个无神论者
The only difference
和罗伯塔唯一的区别在于
between the atheists on TV and Roberta...
罗伯塔是爱你的 她想帮你
is that Roberta loves you. She's trying to help.
不过呢
Tell you what though.
不管是否存在
One way or another,
我们最后都是在一起的
we all end up back together in the end.
这就是你要问的吧
That's what you're asking, right?
是的
Yep.
好
Okay.
这一点你就不用担心了 好吗
Find something else to worry about, will you?
好的
All right.
好 阿德勒 外婆和舅舅
Okay. Adler, grandmother and uncle.
真的吗
Really?
你们真的不打算
You sure you folks don't wanna go out
庭外和解吗
in the hallway and settle this?
那可太遗憾了
No? Well, that's a shame.
卡伦先生 你是这舅舅的律师
Mr. Cullen, you are here for the uncle.
是的 法官大人
Yes, sir, Your Honor.
开始挣你的食宿费了
Start charging you room and board.
海史密斯先生
Mr. Highsmith,
你也是实在太穷了吧
you're on the wrong side of the bay, aren't you?
我很高兴来这里 法官大人
I'm very happy to be here, Your Honor.
声明一下 狄本思夫人
For the record, Mrs. Dibbons
代表佛罗里达州
is representing the State of Florida
儿童福利部门
Child Welfare Department.
开庭
Proceed.
法官大人 我的当事人阿德勒夫人
Your Honor, my client, Mrs. Adler
是这孩子的外婆
is the maternal grandmother of the child.
她女儿 这女孩的母亲
Her daughter, the girl's mother,
患有精神疾病
was a troubled woman...
7年前很不幸的自杀了
who seven years ago, sadly, took her own life.
当时 阿德勒先生
It was at this time that Mr. Adler
抢先而且是非法的
preemptively and illegally...
占据了孩子的监护权
took custody of the girl
带她离开州境
and spirited her across state lines...
以阻止我的当事人行使监护权
for the purpose of denying my client custody.
有证据表明 这孩子目前生活在
Now, there is evidence that the child currently lives...
不干净不健康的环境里
in unclean and unwholesome conditions.
我们请求法庭把孩子的监护权
We petition the court to grant my client
完全判给我的当事人
full custody of the child...
使她能回到
so that she may be returned
马萨诸塞州
to the state of Massachusetts...
得到她应得的照顾
and given the care to which she is entitled.
我的当事人领养这孩子只有一个原因
My client took an infant under his wing for one reason only.
就是这是他姐姐的遗愿
It was his sister's desire that he do so.
我的当事人一直都是她的照顾者
My client has been her constant caregiver.
法官大人 至于孩子的生活环境
And, Your Honor, as far as the living conditions...
我去过他的家 没有问题
I've been in this home. It's fine.
如果我们领养的标准
I mean, if we adopt standards based on...
建立在我们北方的朋友对大蟑螂的厌恶上
our northern friend's aversion to palmetto bugs...
那么塔拉西河南部就不会有一个孩子了
we won't have a child left south of Tallahassee.
再给你们最后一次机会
All right. Last chance before this starts
否则要花大笔律师费了
costing a lot more money.
法官大人 我的当事人
Your Honor, my client would need
需要合理探视权
reasonable access to the child.
法庭批准
So ordered.
狄本思夫人 你会去他家
Ms. Dibbons, you'll go over there
检查一下居住条件吗
and check out the living conditions?
已经计划好了 法官大人
On the books, Your Honor.
好了 各位 小心开车
All right, folks. Drive carefully.
她的律师西装很高档
Her lawyer has a nice suit.
放松 弗兰克 你要更关注我们能力的比较
Relax, Frank. More weight's put on the talent competition.
去喝杯鸡尾酒
Go have a cocktail, hmm?
罗伯塔 你今晚愿意照顾玛丽吗
Roberta, would you like to have Mary tonight?
我为什么会不愿意呢
Why wouldn't I like to have Mary tonight?
我就说过会发生这种事
I told you something like this would happen.
看看我们现在的处境
Now look where we are.
但愿你心里有数
And I'm supposed to believe you know what you're doing.
你连个白人律师都请不起
You couldn't even find a white lawyer.
哇 听着
Wow. Look, just...
- 别担心 好吗 - 少来了
- Don't worry, okay? - Don't tell me that.
你无论说什么
There's nothing you can say
都不会让我好受些
that's gonna make me feel good...
因为这件事上我没有发言权
because I have no say in any of this, Frank.
我不是亲属
I'm not a blood relative,
不是合法监护人 什么都不是
I'm not a legal guardian. I'm nothing!
只是隔壁邻居
Just the lady who lives next door,
我的意见无足轻重
whose opinion means nothing...
我的感受也无足轻重
whose feelings mean nothing.
还问我今晚愿不愿照顾玛丽
Would I like to have Mary tonight?
我每晚都愿意照顾玛丽
I'd like to have Mary every night.
别拦我 现在听我说
∮ Can't stop me now Hear what I say ∮
我要抖腿了 所以
∮ My feets gotta move, so... ∮
给我滚一边去
∮ Get out of my way ∮
我要说我的话
∮ I'm gonna have my say ∮
我要去每一个迪斯科舞厅
∮ I'm going to every discotheque ∮
我要跳舞 跳舞 跳舞 喔
∮ I'm gonna dance, dance, dance Whoo! ∮
一直嗨到天黑
∮ Till the break of day ∮
哦 丢脸 丢脸 丢脸 丢脸
∮ Oh, shame, shame, shame, shame ∮
嗷
∮ Oh! ∮
你真丢脸
∮ Shame on you ∮
如果你也不会跳舞
∮ If you can't dance too ∮
那你真丢脸 丢脸 丢脸 丢脸
∮ And I said shame, shame, shame, shame ∮
丢脸 丢脸 丢脸 你真丢脸
∮ Shame, shame, shame Shame on you ∮
嗨
Hi.
我听戴维斯说到一个监护权的官司
Um, I heard Davis bragging about a custody case
后来我发现是谁
and then I found out whose...
我很内疚
I feel terrible.
但我想告诉你 在我们谈过之后
But I also wanted you to know that after we talked...
我没跟任何人说过什么
I didn't say anything to anyone.
我发誓
I swear.
我很想让你知道这一点
And it's, um, important to me that you know that.
我知道
I know.
好
Okay.
我的律师让我醉一场
My lawyer told me to get drunk.
喝啤酒能喝醉吗
And you're trying to do it with that?
好了 轮到我了
Okay. My turn.
你爱恋的第一个名人是谁
Who was your first celebrity crush?
应该说是
Um, I'll go with...
妙管家 里的莫娜
Mona from Who's the Boss?
哇
Oh, wow!
知道我说的是谁吗
You know who I'm talking about?
- 那个性感的奶奶 - 是的
- The sexy grandmother. - Yeah!
我总感觉她有个秘密
I always felt like she had a secret.
就是她喜欢性爱
Yeah, which is that she loved sexual intercourse.
没错
That was it.
她对此并不隐晦
And she wasn't secret about it.
所以我喜欢她
That's why I liked her.
知道吗 我也喜欢她
You know what? I liked her, too.
看到没
See?
好了
All right. Um...
最不喜欢的学生 以及原因
Least favorite student. And why.
不 每个学生我都喜欢
Oh, no! I love all my students.
我不信 完全不相信
I don't believe you. At all! Not for a second.
他们都很棒
No, they're all great.
都那么棒
They're all so great.
我应该喝酒了
I'm gonna go ahead and drink.
对 这是规矩
Let's keep this honest.
是男生还是女生
He? She?
是罗尼米德尔顿
Uh, he is Ronnie Middleton.
一听就不是好人
Sounds like a dick.
- 他只是个孩子好吗 - 对不起
- He's a little child, okay? - I'm sorry.
关键是他是骨子里坏
The point is that he's evil in his core.
而我对此无能为力
And there's nothing I can do.
哇
Wow.
你最怕什么
What's your greatest fear?
哇
Wow!
基调变了啊
That's a change of tone.
是的 我是个很严肃的人
Yup, I'm a really serious person.
好
Okay.
如果难以回答 你直接喝酒就是
Look, if it's too much, you can just drink your drink...
承认自己的害怕
and live with the fact that you're afraid.
我能应付
No, I can handle this. Um...
害怕我会毁了玛丽这一生
That I'll ruin Mary's life.
你非常
You're very, um...
令人意外 玛丽的老师
surprising, Mary's teacher.
非常令人意外
Very much so.
- 等一下 抱歉 - 怎么了
- Okay. Hold on. I'm sorry. - What?
就是
Just so that...
我觉得有句话要提前声明一下
I feel like I need to say this...
来消除误解
just so that there's no misconception.
我并没有
Oh, God. No, I didn't...
等一下
No, hold on!
我们之间是不可能的
That this can't, isn't happening.
我懂 我赞同
I get it. I know. I'm with you.
- 是吗 - 我完全赞同
- Yeah? Okay. - 100%. We're on the same page.
很好
Good!
这很好 抱歉 这很尴尬
No, that's great. I'm sorry. That's embarrassing.
没关系 我懂
It's okay. I get it.
啊
Oh!
- 你没事吧 - 我没事
- Are you okay? - Yeah, I'm good.
好
Okay. Good.
你能保证玛丽不可能来吗
Can you promise that there's no way?
每周五晚玛丽都在罗伯塔家
Yes. Roberta has Mary
直到周六中午 我保证
every Saturday till noon, I promise.
是吗
Yeah?
抱歉
Mmm. Mmm-mmm. Sorry.
我不能这么做
I can't do this.
好
Okay.
我理解
I understand.
我送你回家
I'll take you home.
好
Yeah.
抱歉 再亲一口
Sorry, just... One more time.
我找不到我的DVD了
I can't find my DVD.
就在那儿
It's right there, baby.
不在 不信你来找找
No, it isn't. You come and find it.
我忙着呢
I'm doing lady business.
你是最后一个看它的人
Now, you were the last person to watch it.
你把它放在哪儿了
What did you do with it?
对了
Oh...
天啊
Oh! Oh, my God!
早上好 史蒂文斯老师
Good morning, Miss Stevenson.
嗨
Hi.
听着 我…
Look, I am...
知道吗 我现在
Oh, you know what? I'm actually incapable...
没法谈这事
of having this conversation right now.
很好 我也正愁该说啥好
Good. 'Cause I have no idea what I was gonna say.
很好 很好
Great! Perfect!
师傅 走吧 送我去监狱
Sir, if you please. Take me to jail.
尴尬啊
Awkward.
玛丽
Mary...
停下 停下
Stop! Stop!
别玩积木了 听我说
Stop with the Legos! Listen.
我们周六上午不是有规定吗
Do we have a rule about Saturday morning?
什么
What?
我允许你周六上午进来吗
Are you allowed in this apartment this early
允不允许
on Saturday morning? Yes or no?
- 不允许 - 不允许
- No. - No!
我允许你… 喂
Are you allowed...Hi
停下 别玩积木了
Stop! Enough with the Legos.
我允许你用罗伯塔的钥匙吗
Are you allowed to use Roberta's keys?
- 不允许 - 不允许
- No. - No!
喂 看着我
Hey! Look at me.
那你为什么来这里
Then why are you here, huh?
能回答我这个问题吗
Can you answer me that?
你违反了所有的规矩
You broke every rule!
你让我难堪
You just embarrassed me.
我们有这些规矩的
We have these rules.
我说过无数次了
We've gone over them a hundred times! Ahh!
啊
God!
该死的
Damn it!
我就不能有一点自己的生活吗
Can I just get five minutes of my own life?
今天发生的事完全不是你的错
Nothing that happened today was your fault.
我生你的气
I got mad at you...
我也很生自己的气
I was really mad at me.
生产乐高积木的商家
And the manufacturers of Legos,
他们都该进监狱
they should all be in prison.
对不起
I'm sorry.
你原谅我吗
Do you forgive me?
好 随便
Sure. Whatever.
喂 关上电脑 快点
Hey, close the laptop. Come on.
拜托 互相看着说话才算
Please. Doesn't count if it's not eye to eye.
拜托
Come on, please.
有了我 所以你没有自己的生活了吗
Do you really have no life because of me?
我没这么说
That's not what I said.
嗯
Hmm.
你是真心话吗
Did you mean it?
你上个月说过
Last month you said I was
我是世上最差的舅舅
the worst uncle in the world...
你希望我死
and you wished death upon me
因为我没给你买钢琴
'cause I didn't buy you a piano.
你是真心话吗
Did you mean that?
不是
No.
不完全是
Not entirely.
那就是了
There you go.
我们并非每句话都是真心话
We say things all the time we don't mean. So...
我们忘了这件事 好吗
Let's forget it, okay?
好
Okay.
弗兰克
Frank?
什么
Yeah?
能给我买架钢琴吗
Can I have a piano?
不行
No.
今早真是玛丽的老师吗
Was that really Mary's teacher this morning?
我有本书
You know, I got a book called
人生基本决策
Fundamentals of Decision Making.
你可以借去看看
You can borrow it.
是什么
What is it?
没什么
It's nothing.
看来玛丽要去波士顿几天了
Looks like Mary gets to go to Boston for a couple days.
就两天
It's just two days.
你放心
Relax.
你觉得怎么样
So, what do you think?
很棒
Cool.
哇 你和我妈妈
Wow! You and my mom...
总是在一起
were always together.
总是
Always.
不 这张不要看
Oh, no, you don't want to look at that one.
这是你吗
Is that you?
是的
Yes.
你当时多大
How old were you?
29岁
29.
这是在哪儿
Where is this?
这是剑桥大学
That's Cambridge University.
在英国
In England.
这些人是谁
Who are those people?
我的研究同事
My research colleagues.
研究什么
For what?
当然是数学
Mathematics, of course.
真的吗
Really?
好棒
Cool!
那你后来
So, then you came to work...
就来美国大学工作了?
at a college in America?
不是
No.
我嫁给了你外公
I married your grandfather...
跟他一起回到美国
and I came back to America with him.
然后生了孩子
And I had children.
哦
Oh.
不再研究数学了
So, no more math?
不早了
It's late.
你明天还有重要的事
You've got a big day tomorrow.
来 起来
Come on. Up, up, up.
我能弹钢琴吗
Can I play the piano?
不行
No, you can't.
- 别拖着脚了 - 可是钢琴好玩
- Now stop dragging those feet. - But, it's fun!
快走
Come on!
我做了一连串的噩梦
I have had a series of nightmares...
因为那件事
where I'm fired...
我被学校开除了
because of what happened.
你明白吗
You get it?
然后我试图解释
And then I try to rationalize...
那只是因为我喝醉了
that everything that happened was just all alcohol.
我对修理工有好感
I have an addiction to fixer guys.
尚克兰博士 这道题…
Dr. Shankland, this problem is...
我知道 原题照抄下来就是了
I know. Just copy it exactly as you see it written.
可这题…
But it's...
照抄原题 谢谢
Exactly as written. Thank you.
要让我看什么数学题
So, what's this problem I'm supposed to look at?
不知道
I don't know.
就像妈妈研究的那些问题吗
Is it like the problems Mom worked on?
你妈研究的不是一些问题
Your mother didn't work on problems.
她只研究了一个问题
She worked on just one problem.
就一个吗
Just one?
研究了一辈子
Her entire life?
大部分
Most of it.
看
Look.
这些都是千年难题
These are the Millennium Problems.
七个意义重大的难题
Seven great and meaningful problems.
有些数学家
Some mathematicians have worked
用了一辈子时间来证明
their entire lives to prove them.
这个大胡子是谁
Who's the dude with the beard?
他可不是普通人
That's not a dude.
他是格里戈里・佩雷尔曼
That's Grigori Perelman.
他证明了庞加莱猜想
He proved the Poincaré conjecture.
七个问题中唯一一个得到证明的
The only one of the seven proved.
这个
This...
这是你妈研究的问题
This is your mother's problem.
纳维…
Na... vi...
纳维尔-斯托克斯方程
Navier-Stokes.
没照片啊
No picture.
- 她没证明吗 - 没有
- She didn't solve it? - No.
她当时快证明出来了
She was close.
她本来可以获得菲尔茨奖
She would have won the Fields Medal...
还可能分享诺贝尔奖
and probably shared a Nobel...
因为在物理学上也有重要意义
considering what it would have meant for physics.
也许将来我的照片也能挂在上面
Maybe I'll have my picture up here someday.
如果你真的想
If you really desire it...
你可以把你的照片挂在上面 孩子
you can have your picture there, darling.
我可以帮你
I can help you.
这需要专注和刻苦 但如果你成功了
It takes focus and hard work, but if you succeed...
你将流芳百世
your name will live forever.
先别得意 西摩
Don't be smug, Seymore.
她看了很长时间了
Well, she's had plenty of time.
她昨天出了远门 没睡好
She traveled yesterday. She slept in a strange bed.
给她个机会
Give her a chance.
她6岁就看过奇默的书
At six years old, she read Zimmer.
厉害
Outstanding.
她看懂了多少
How much did she comprehend?
玛丽
So, Mary...
你在看我们的小问题
I see you're looking at our little problem.
小问题? 这是个大问题
Little? It's big.
是啊
Yeah.
你怎么突然这么生气
Why are you so mad all of a sudden?
我不是生气 是恼火
I'm not mad. I'm annoyed.
不是恼火你
Not with you, dear.
是恼火那个傲慢的尚克兰
With that pompous ass, Shankland.
我们还没进去
I knew that guy was gonna have a beard
就知道他是个大胡子
before we even went in there.
数学老师都喜欢长胡子
Math teachers like to grow beards.
我当初就不该答应这事
I should never have agreed to this in the first place.
他真的指望你
Did he really expect you
随随便便就能解析
to just walk in and be able to dissect...
某个随机的复杂难题
some random, massive problem?
我看也没什么可解析的
Not much to dissect, if you ask me.
为什么这么说
Why do you say that?
题错了
It was wrong.
什么
What?
首先
Well, for starters,
他忘了加上指数前的负号
he forgot the negative sign on the exponent.
后面就讲不通了
It went downhill from there.
这道题没法解
The problem was unsolvable.
也许这学校也不怎么样
Maybe this school isn't as great as you think it is.
玛丽 既然你知道题是错的
Mary, you knew the problem was incorrect.
怎么不早说呢
Why didn't you say anything?
弗兰克说我不要去指出长辈的错误
Frank says I'm not supposed to correct older people.
没人喜欢自作聪明的人
Nobody likes a smart-ass.
我带了好多好东西
I'm loaded with swag!
要进屋坐吗
Wanna come inside?
猫
Cat.
弗兰克 我觉得这样很傻
Frank, I think this is stupid.
我们给伊芙琳打电话
Why don't we just call Evelyn
说我不愿意不就成了吗
and tell her I don't wanna do this?
因为我说过
Because like I told you,
伊芙琳说的不算 这是法庭判的
Evelyn didn't order this. The court did.
那么我们该怎么办
So again, what are we gonna do?
说实话
Tell the truth.
没错
Exactly.
我们越早回答这些问题
Sooner we answer these questions,
就能越早回家
sooner we get to go home.
要配合 好吗
So, no attitude, okay?
好
Okay.
弗兰克
Frank?
玛丽
Mary.
我喜欢伊芙琳
I like Evelyn.
她长得像我妈妈
She looks like my mom.
而且她还有钢琴
And she has a piano.
可我不想跟她一起住
But I don't wanna live with her.
她很专横
She's bossy.
这话我听过
I've heard that.
喂
Hey.
你放心 你哪儿都不会去
Don't worry. You're not going anywhere.
你保证?
Promise?
我保证
I promise.
嗨 玛丽 我叫帕特戈尔丁
Hi, Mary. I'm Pat Golding,
你叫我帕特就行
but you can call me Pat if you like.
知道了
Got it.
你知道你为什么来吗
Do you know why you're here?
有人说过是为了什么事吗
I mean has anyone told you what this is about?
我外婆希望我跟她一起住
My grandmother wants me to live with her
而我想跟弗兰克一起住
and I wanna stay with Frank.
很好
That's correct.
我知道这可能挺可怕的
I'm sure this can all be very scary stuff.
你担心过吗
Does any of it worry you?
不担心 弗兰克说我哪儿也不去
Nope. Frank says I'm not goin' anywhere.
你舅舅说你哪儿都不去
Your uncle told you you're not going anywhere?
15分钟之前说的
Just 15 minutes ago.
我们谈完了吗
So, we done here?
还没有
Not quite yet.
除了弗兰克和弗雷德 我最好的朋友就是罗伯塔
My best friend other than Frank and Fred is Roberta...
她住在我家附近
who lives a couple houses away.
是吗 她是什么样的人
Really? What's she like?
她和善 风趣 我喜欢她
She's nice and funny. And I love her.
那挺好
That's nice.
罗伯塔是你唯一的同龄朋友吗
Is Roberta your only friend your age?
罗伯塔跟我不同龄 她大概40 50
Roberta's not my age. She's like 40, 50...
30多岁的样子
30-something.
罗伯塔是个成年人?
Roberta's a grown woman?
我的同龄人都很无趣
People my age are boring.
罗伯塔很棒
Roberta's cool.
好
Okay.
我不看电视
I don't watch TV.
但我喜欢海绵宝宝
But I got hooked on SpongeBob.
主要是因为罗伯塔喜欢
Mostly because Roberta loves it.
对了 我们周六晚上会看UFC
Oh. And on Saturday nights, we watch the UFC.
UFC? 是不是…
The UFC? Is that...
是终极格斗吗
Is that Ultimate Fighting?
每周六都看
Every Saturday.
你和你舅看终极格斗?
You and your uncle watch Ultimate Fighting?
不只是看
Well, you don't just watch it.
弗兰克把声音调低
Frank turns the sound down
我们俩来配音
and we do the grunting and voices.
有时我真的用力打弗兰克
Sometimes I attack Frank for real.
对我来说很开心
Which is really fun for me.
如果你们了解弗兰克
I think if you guys knew Frank,
就会让我们住在一起了
you'd leave us alone.
他虽然有时很烦人
He can be pretty annoying...
但他是个好人
but he's a good person.
应该是吧
I think.
为什么这么说
Why do you say that?
我聪明之前他就喜欢我
He wanted me before I was smart.
波拉德先生
Mr. Pollard, are you...
你是玛丽阿德勒的生父吗
the natural father of Mary Adler?
是的
Yes, I am.
你何以确定
And how can you be certain of this?
我一直知道 后来你们让我
Well, I always knew, but then you had me...
做了DNA测试
take a DNA test.
我想提供测试结果
I would offer the test results
证明波拉德先生
as presumptive evidence that Mr. Pollard...
是这孩子的生父和自然监护人
is the father and natural guardian of the minor.
同时作为证言
As well as an affidavit...
波拉德先生提出
from Mr. Pollard nominating...
让孩子的外婆阿德勒夫人
Mrs. Adler, the maternal grandmother,
为孩子的法定监护人
as the legal guardian of the minor.
没有反对
No objections.
波拉德先生
Mr. Pollard...
阿德勒夫人给过你任何金钱
has Mrs. Adler offered you any monetary reward...
或职位来请你出庭吗
or employment for coming forward today?
没有 我自己有工作
No, sir. I have a job of my own.
谢谢
Thank you.
没别的问题了 法官大人
No further questions, Your Honor.
波拉德先生
Mr. Pollard...
你最后一次见到玛丽是什么时候
when was the last time you saw Mary?
呃 我从未见过她
Uh... I've never seen her.
为什么
Oh, why not?
当我听说黛安…
By the time I heard about Diane...
去世时
passing...
孩子已经不在了
the baby was gone already.
你试图找过她吗
Well, did you try and find her?
尽力找了
Best I could.
我总不能找遍全国吧
I couldn't just go and search the entire country.
你上班用电脑吗
Do you use a computer at work?
当然
Sure.
那你帮我个忙
You know what? Help me out.
搜索一下玛丽阿德勒
Here, let's google "Mary Adler"
看看能搜到什么
and, uh, see what we find.
这样吧
You know what?
最好把她的中间名也加进去
Uh, you better add her middle name.
能缩小搜索范围
It'll narrow it down.
是艾琳
Eileen.
对 点击搜索
Yeah. Hit Enter.
第二页
Page 2.
第二条
Second hit.
你能告诉法庭你看到了什么吗
Would you please tell the court what you see there?
是一篇报纸文章 题为
It's a newspaper article called
非典型两岁儿童
"Not So Terrible Twos."
其中一个就是玛丽艾琳阿德勒
And one of them is Mary Eileen Adler.
跟你女儿同名
Same name as your daughter.
和你女儿同一天生日
Born on the same day as your daughter.
还有照片
With a photograph.
当然你不可能认得出来
Um, in your defense, you'd never recognize it...
- 法官大人 这… - 法官大人
- Your Honor, this is... - Your Honor...
很明显的一点是
if there's one thing here that's sadly obvious...
波拉德先生从来不是
it's that Mr. Pollard has never been
孩子的真正监护人
a genuine guardian of the minor...
他对阿德勒夫人的提名
and his nomination of Mrs. Adler
也是没有诚意的
is no less disingenuous.
佛罗里达州尊重
While the State of Florida gives deference
孩子父母的提名
to nomination by a natural parent...
但这次我倾向于支持
I'm inclined to side with Mr. Cullen's laptop...
卡伦先生的笔记本电脑
at this time.
谢谢你 法官大人
Thank you, Your Honor.
别得意
Don't gloat.
想都不敢想
Wouldn't dream of it.
送你去车上
Walk you to your car?
刚才忙着打官司 我不好意思问
We've been so preoccupied, I'm almost ashamed to ask.
沃尔特还好吗
How's Walter?
说了恐怕你也不信
You wouldn't believe it if I told you.
怎么了
Why?
你的继父在蒙大拿
Well, your stepfather is in Montana.
他买了个农场
He bought a ranch.
扯淡
Bullshit.
可不是嘛 他认为只要远离
Exactly. A man whose idea of roughing it...
丽思卡尔顿酒店的制冰机 那就是返璞归真
is being too far from the ice machine at the Ritz-Carlton...
他现在拥有着1000英亩的草地和牛粪
now owns a 1,000 acres of grass and dung.
沃特尔普莱斯成了个牛仔
Walter Price is a cowboy.
沃尔特穿着布克兄弟西装
Walter Price puts on a Brooks Brothers suit
去倒垃圾
to take out the garbage.
他有顶牛仔帽和一双牛仔靴
He has a cowboy hat and cowboy boots...
和一匹不会马术的马
and a horse that doesn't know dressage.
他为什么这么做呢
Is there some logical reason for this?
可能是中年危机吧
Midlife crisis, apparently.
他都70岁了
He's 70.
可不是嘛
I know.
肯定是延迟了吧
Must have been on time delay or something.
我应该高兴才是
I guess I should be happy
毕竟他不是有了小三
it wasn't a 25-year-old cocktail waitress.
但话说回来
But then again,
如果是婚外情 我三言两语就能向朋友解释清
an affair you can explain to friends in a minute.
但这事 要花很长时间才能让别人听明白
For this, you put on a pot of coffee.
他现在去体验荒野了
And he's out there right now?
是的
Yessiree!
骑马 放牧
Ridin' the range. Punchin' doggies.
腰上别着一把左轮手枪
He had a six gun on his hip...
马褡裢上装满了立普妥
and a saddlebag full of Lipitor.
西部最快的资产管理
The fastest asset management in the West.
开枪打了利宝保险的人
The man who shot Liberty Mutual.
我一直都这么称呼他
That's what I've been calling him.
这事确实很扯淡
That's really, really funny.
送她去机场
Take her to the airport.
回家去吧 伊芙琳
Go home, Evelyn.
或者去蒙大拿放牛
Or Montana. Rustle some cattle.
你知道
You know...
我完全不想伤害你
I have no desire to hurt you.
我不喜欢跟你发生冲突
I hate it that we're at odds.
我们老是在冲突
We're always at odds.
是的
Yes.
酒店
Hotel.
玛丽 孩子 拜托
Mary, baby, come on now.
别哭了
Stop this now.
不
No.
- 出来吧 - 不
- Come on out, honey. - No.
你干嘛跟她说她爸爸也出庭了
Why did you have to tell her that deadbeat was testifying?
因为这是事实
Because it's the truth.
如果我不说 伊芙琳也会说的
And if I didn't, Evelyn would've.
如果我是父亲 有个女儿
If I was the dad of a little girl
从未见过
and I never saw her...
而且住在同一个城市
and I was in the same town...
我肯定会去看她
I would visit her.
这下你满意了
Well, I hope you're happy.
他根本不需要问路
He didn't even need directions.
跟着你来就是了
He could've followed you here.
这就是所说的渣男人
Speaking of men who aren't worth a damn.
他甚至不想看到我的样子
Doesn't even wanna see what I look like.
好了
All right.
喂 你穿上鞋 我们开车出去一下
Hey, put your shoes on. We're going for a ride.
你也是
You too.
开车出去
A ride?
我们来这里干什么
What are we doing here?
等着
Waiting.
这是废话
We can see that.
为什么等
Why?
因为我让你们等着
Because I said so.
我们要等多久
How long do we have to stay here?
需要多久就多久
As long as it takes.
说话小点声 这里是医院
And keep your voice down. It's a hospital.
- 吃的来了 - 是啊 吃的来了
- Food's here. - Yeah, food's here.
是个男孩
It's a boy.
好样的
Way to go!
你出生时就是这个情景
That's exactly how it was when you were born.
这么开心吗
This happy?
这么开心
This happy.
当时是谁出来跟大家说的
Who came out and told everybody?
是我
I did.
我们再等着看一个吧
Can we stay for another?
阿德勒夫人 在你今天之前的证词中
Mrs. Adler, in your earlier testimony, here today...
你把自己的儿子说的很不堪
you've painted a pretty dim picture of your own son.
不是吗
Don't you think?
我是宣过誓的
I'm under oath.
我也不想说这些话
I take no pleasure in it.
那么你儿子的人生失败
So, your son's a failure in life,
你女儿自杀了
your daughter took her life.
你算是失败两次了
You know, you're oh for two.
- 我反对 - 撤回
- Objection! - Withdrawn.
如果我有第三个孩子 我会进名人堂了
If I go one for three, I'm in the Hall of Fame.
你了解棒球
You know baseball.
芬威球场
Fenway Park.
我很想有时间去那里看看
You know, I'd like to go there some time.
你一年带着黛安
How often in a year
去看几次棒球比赛
did you take Diane to a baseball game?
黛安对体育不感兴趣
Diane wasn't interested in sports.
她从不想去看比赛 一次也没有
She never wanted to go to a game? Ever?
我不记得她要求过
I don't recall her ever asking.
我有些好奇 芬威球场的票不好买
Just out of curiosity, Fenway, that's a tough ticket.
你的票是怎么买到的
Where do you get yours?
我丈夫有季票
My husband has season tickets.
他有季票多长时间
And how long has he had them?
30年
30 years.
但我跟他结婚20年
But I've only been married to him for 20.
黛安一场比赛都没去看过
And Diane never went to one game?
黛安是穿什么颜色的裙子参加毕业舞会的
What color was the dress Diane wore to prom?
黛安没参加毕业舞会
Diane didn't attend a prom
因为她没上高中
because she didn't go to a high school.
没参加毕业舞会
No prom.
她喜欢什么体育运动
What sports did she play?
我刚才说了
As I told you earlier,
她对体育不感兴趣
she wasn't interested in sports.
她去过夏令营吗
Did she go to camp during the summer?
没有
No.
- 社区游泳池呢 - 我家有游泳池
- Community swimming pool? - We had our own pool.
- 女童子军呢 - 没有
- Girl Scouts? - No.
那么她这些年来都干什么
Then what did she do with all that time?
她喜欢数学 那是她的爱好
She loved mathematics. It was her passion.
她喜欢数学胜过一切
She preferred it to all other things.
一切
All other?
阿德勒夫人 保罗里瓦是谁
Mrs. Adler, who's Paul Riva?
他是邻居家的男孩
He was a boy from the neighborhood.
拜托 他可远不只是
Oh, come on. He was much more than...
邻居家的男孩
just a boy from the neighborhood.
保罗是黛安的初恋
Paul was Diane's first love...
对吗
wasn't he?
我不这么看 不是
I wouldn't characterize it that way. No.
黛安是怎么看的
And how would Diane characterize it?
黛安当时才17岁
Diane was 17 years old at the time.
对爱情一无所知
She didn't know anything about love.
阿德勒夫人
Mrs. Adler...
在1998年1月
in January of 1998...
黛安是不是和年轻的里瓦先生私奔了
didn't Diane and young Mr. Riva run away together?
他强迫她的
He coerced her.
- 他们去了哪里 - 佛蒙特
- And where did they go? - Vermont.
你报警了 是不是
And you called the police, didn't you?
- 因为他绑架了她 - 是的
- Because he kidnapped her? - Yes. Yes.
警方在哪里找到了里瓦先生和黛安
And where did the police find young Mr. Riva and Diane?
我说过了 是在佛蒙特
I told you. Vermont.
是佛蒙特的斯托吧
Stowe, Vermont. Wasn't it?
一个旅游小镇
A resort town.
斯托山
Stowe Mountain.
他带她去滑雪
He took her skiing.
绑架者一般不会
You see, kidnappers don't usually
带被绑架人去滑雪
take their victims skiing.
但保罗是这么做的
But this is what Paul did...
因为他和黛安在相爱
because he and Diane were in love.
不
No.
他们回来后
And when they returned,
你指控他绑架
you pressed kidnapping charges.
你起诉了他父母
You filed a lawsuit against his parents...
直到保罗不再跟黛安打电话了
until Paul stopped calling Diane.
- 是不是 - 是的
- Didn't you? - Yes.
后来黛安跟保罗就再也没有来往了
And Diane never heard from or saw Paul Riva again.
是不是
Did she?
据我所知没有
Not to my knowledge.
她对此反应如何
And how did she take it?
她消沉了一段时间
She was upset for a while.
心不在焉
She lost focus.
阿德勒夫人 1999年3月
Mrs. Adler, in March of 1999...
黛安是不是试图自杀过
didn't Diane Adler attempt to take her own life?
那次是小事 没什么要紧的
This episode was minor. It was nothing.
我手上拿着医院的记录
I have the hospital report in my hand.
那没什么要紧的
It was nothing.
黛安跟普通人不一样
Diane was not like regular people.
她是特殊的人
She was extraordinary.
而特殊的人
And extraordinary people
会有一些特别的障碍和需求
come with singular issues and needs.
你根本不知道她的才能有多强
You have no idea the capability she possessed.
亿里挑一的人才
One in a billion.
难道你会说 不要这些才能了
And you would say, "Fine, let's throw that away...
任由为我家修剪草坪的男孩勾引她吧
"so the boy who cuts our yard can make a sexual conquest."
在你做决定之前
Maybe before you make that decision,
站在我的角度想想
you stand in my shoes.
我的责任远不只是
I had responsibilities which went beyond
一个母亲的责任
the mother-daughter relationship.
为人类带来进步的
The greatest discoveries
那些最伟大的发现
which have improved life on this planet...
都是出自极为罕见的人才
have come from minds rarer than radium.
没有他们的话 人类依然会茹毛饮血
Without them, we'd still be crawling in mud.
告诉你 律师
And for your information, counselor...
在这男孩的事结束一年之后
a year after this incident with this boy...
黛安感谢了我对她的干涉
Diane thanked me for my intervention.
她明白她犯了个错误 并感谢了我
She realized she'd made a mistake and she thanked me.
黛安明白她有责任
You see, Diane understood she was accountable
去发挥自己的天赋
for the gift she'd been given.
她也没有逃避
And she didn't shy from it.
如果她今天能在法庭上
And I think, if she were here today, Mr. Attorney...
她会驳斥你毫无根据的影射
she would refute your baseless insinuations...
说她放弃远大的前程
that she would give up her brilliant future
选择自杀
and take her own life...
只因为她妈妈没给她买一辆红色童车
just because Mommy didn't get her a little red wagon.
我没问题了
No more questions.
阿德勒先生
Mr. Adler...
你目前在哪里工作
where are you currently employed?
我修船
I repair boats.
是吗 在哪个船坞
Oh, really? At which marina?
不是船坞 我是打零工的
I don't work at a marina. I freelance.
那么你没有医疗保险
So, safe to say, no health insurance.
没有
No.
你姐姐自杀之前大约一周
About a week before your sister took her life...
你是做什么职业的
what were you doing for a living then?
我是老师
I was a teacher.
这话太谦虚了吧
You're being modest, aren't you?
你当时是波士顿大学的教授
You were a professor at Boston University...
是吗
isn't that right?
是的 是助理教授
Yes, well, Assistant Professor.
你教什么
And what'd you teach?
哲学
Philosophy.
事实和逻辑 这方面内容的吧
Truth and logic. That sort of thing.
你的律师说你收养玛丽
Your attorney said that the primary reason...
主要原因是你姐姐
that you took Mary is because it was what your sister...
希望你这么做 这是事实吗
would have wanted you to do. Is that the truth?
是的
Yes.
那么黛安以前来过Pinellas县
So Diane had visited Pinellas County before?
没有
No.
她说过希望女儿
Indicated she wanted her daughter
搬到这里吗
uprooted and moved here?
- 没有 - 没有
- No. - No.
那么是你决定把玛丽带到这里 是不是
So, you decided to bring Mary here, didn't you?
黛安对你在波士顿大学的
Did Diane have a problem
医疗保险有异议吗
with your health plan at Boston University?
据我所知没有
Not to my knowledge.
你觉得她会希望女儿
Do you think she would want her daughter
有医疗保险吗
to have access to healthcare?
当然
Of course.
那么玛丽生病的时候你怎么办
So what do you do, when little Mary gets sick?
去给医生修船吗
You repair a doctor's boat?
- 我反对 - 反对有效
- Objection. - Sustained.
玛丽被认为是
Mary has been identified...
数学天才
as a math prodigy.
但在你的监护下 她接受的正规数学教育
But her formal math education under your care...
只是一年级水平 对吗
she's learning at the first grade level, isn't she?
是的
Yes.
而你拒绝了橡树学校的奖学金
And you turned down a scholarship at the Oaks...
一所专门教育天才儿童的学校
a school specializing in the education of gifted children?
是的
Yes.
黛安对此会同意吗
And Diane, she'd be fine with that?
我没法说
I couldn't say.
阿德勒夫人给玛丽电脑前
Prior to Mrs. Adler giving her one,
她自己有电脑吗
did Mary have a computer?
她用我的电脑
She used mine.
阿德勒先生 黛安的女儿有自己的卧室吗
Mr. Adler, does Diane's daughter have her own bedroom?
没有
No.
她睡的床是不是你
Does she sleep in a bed that you bought...
- 从二手店买的 - 是的
- in a secondhand shop? - Yes.
那么事实就是 阿德勒先生
So, the truth is, Mr. Adler,
你搬到这里不是因为
that you didn't come down here
你姐姐希望你搬来
because your sister wanted you to...
也不是因为
and you certainly didn't come here
这是为了玛丽着想
because it was good for Mary.
不 是出于私人感情
No, it was personal.
黛安是明星 而你不是
Diane was a star. You weren't.
黛安受人关注 而你没有
Diane got the attention. You didn't.
这些年来 你变得易怒
And over the years, you got angry.
后来有了玛丽
And here comes Mary.
真是报复的好机会
What a great way to get even.
你把那小女孩
You've uprooted that little girl
带到这里 只有一个原因
and brought her here for one reason only.
是为了伤害你母亲
To do harm to your mother.
你把姐姐的死怪在她身上
You blamed her for your sister.
我没有
No, I don't.
玛丽只是你用来报复的工具 是吗
And Mary to you is just a pawn in all this. Isn't she?
黛安希望玛丽
Diane wanted Mary...
做个普通孩子
to be a kid.
希望她能有完整的人生
She wanted her to have a life.
希望她能有朋友
She wanted her to have friends...
能玩
and to play...
能幸福
and to be happy.
你知道平淡的生活
Do you realize the consequences
会让天才儿童怎么样吗
of boredom for a gifted child, Mr. Adler?
他们会变得易怒 郁闷
They become resentful and sullen.
玛丽不是易怒的孩子
Mary's not an angry kid.
是吗
Really?
她没在校车上打过一个孩子吗
Did she not attack a child on the school bus?
一个12岁的孩子
A 12-year-old tripped
绊倒了一个7岁孩子 她站出来维护他
a 7- year- old and she came to his defense.
- 她是不是把那男孩鼻子打破了 - 是的
- Did she break the boy's nose? - Yes.
去年10月16日 你是不是因为伤人被捕了
On October 16th of last year were you arrested for assault?
天啊
Oh, my God.
你必须回答问题 阿德勒先生
NICHOLS: You have to answer the question, Mr. Adler.
一个喝醉的笨蛋打我 我是自卫
A drunk idiot attacked me and I defended myself.
这跟黛安有什么关系
What does that have to do with anything?
你是不是被拘留了一晚
Did you spend the night in jail?
是的
Yeah.
你真是不自量力
You are in way over your head here.
你剥夺了她的未来
You're depriving that girl.
拿她的前程做赌注
You're gambling with her future...
现在你有了机会
and now you're being presented with an opportunity...
能好好待她
to do right by her. Jump at it.
律师对我的当事人有问题吗
Does counsel have a question for my client?
做出明智的选择 阿德勒先生
Take the high road, Mr. Adler...
趁她还能挽救
before she is irreparably damaged.
律师对我的当事人
Does counsel have a question...
- 到底有没有问题 - 有 先生
- for my client or not? - Yes, sir.
我确实有个问题
I do have the question.
告诉我们 你继续做监护人
Tell us, is your continued guardianship...
真的是对她最好的吗
really in the best interest of this little girl?
是的
Yes.
Yes, it is.
我没别的问题了
I have no further questions.
研发部
Research and Development...
发明了一种全新的弗雷德加油
has come up with a brand new Fred cheer.
弗雷德问过我会不会告诉你
Fred personally asked me if I would tell you it.
让我听听
Let's hear it.
加油 为我加油 弗雷德
S-O-C-K I-T Sock it to me, Freddy...
加油
Sock it.
告诉研发部 他们成功了
Tell R and D, they got a winner.
我也是这么说的
That's exactly what I said.
加油 为我加油 弗雷德
S-O-C-K I-T Sock it to me, Freddy
他们想达成协议
They wanna cut a deal.
海史密斯今天一早给我打了电话
Highsmith called me first thing this morning.
他为什么要这样 我不明白
Why would he do that? I don't understand.
现在正在…
In the middle of...
听着 听我说
Just listen. Listen to me, man.
把玛丽送到一个寄养家庭
Mary would be put in a fostering situation.
不行
No.
- 拜托 弗兰克 - 不行
- Come on, Frank. - Cullen, I told you no.
这不是法庭指定的
It wouldn't be a court- appointed
寄养家庭 弗兰克
foster family, Frank.
- 别说了 - 我们可以选择
- Hey! Drop it! - We could cherry-pick...
最好的寄养家庭
from the cream of the crop.
双方都同意的家庭
Mutually approved.
听我说完
Just hear me out.
必须在坦帕
Tampa.
我坚持这一点 他们也同意了
I insisted, and they agreed.
距离你家不能超过半小时车程
No more than a half an hour from your front door.
她要去橡树学校上学
Now, she would attend the Oaks.
那是所好学校
It's a great school.
外婆有探视权
And visiting rights for the grandmother...
但她总能得到探视权的
but she was gonna get that anyway.
等她满12岁之后
Right? And on her 12th birthday, Frank,
她可以重回法庭
she can go back into court...
- 不行 - 然后决定
- No. - and decide then...
她想跟谁住在一起
where she wants to live and with who.
我不明白
I don't understand this.
你本该站在我这一边的
I thought you were supposed to be on my team.
为什么跟我谈这个协议
Why are you bringing me this deal?
这是法律规定我必须做的
Other than I'm required to by law?
你觉得这协议有利?
You like this deal?
太有利了
I love this deal.
他们担心会输掉官司
They think they're gonna lose.
是的
Yeah.
他们是的
They do.
你也担心我们会输
You think we're gonna lose.
是的
Yes.
我是的 弗兰克
I do, Frank.
我要去哄孩子睡觉了
I gotta go put my kids to bed.
你让我干什么我就干什么
I'll do whatever you want me to do.
但如果这案子让尼克尔斯法官来判决的话
But if we leave this up to that judge, Nichols...
他很传统 弗兰克
he's old school, Frank.
他喜欢你母亲的为人吗 不
Does he like your mother? No.
但他喜欢她的收入吗
Does he like her income?
喜欢她的医疗保险吗 喜欢她的住宅吗
Does he like her health plan? Does he like her home?
那是肯定的
You better believe it.
我去过他的法庭
I've been in his courtroom.
很多次了
A hundred times.
如果他要二选一的话
And if it's a coin toss...
看着我
Look at me.
如果他要二选一的话
If it's a coin toss...
这老头会倾向于钱
that old boy is going to side with the money.
就当帮我个忙 弗兰克
So, do me a favor, Frank.
去寄养家庭看看 看看感觉如何
Just meet the family. See how it feels.
我只有这个要求
It's all I ask.
飞吧 美丽的小鸟
∮ Fly away, little pretty bird ∮
快快飞走吧
∮ Fly, fly away... ∮
泳池 佛罗里达
Pool. Florida.
码头在海岸之间
That dock is on the Intercoastal.
我觉得这很明显
Which I guess is obvious...
因为我们就住在海岸之间
since we're on the Intercoastal.
这是新添的书桌 让她可以做作业
Added this desk, so she could do her homework.
是啊
Yeah.
这里将是她的卧室
And this would be her room.
在你眼中我看到希望
∮ I see in your eyes a promise ∮
我一直对你说这房子的好处
So, while I'm trying to sell you on the house...
说我们的好处
and us...
只为了让你知道
I just don't want you to think
我们完全理解
that we're completely insensitive...
你的感受
to what you're feeling.
你们家里养猫没问题吧
You guys gonna be okay with a cat?
没问题
Absolutely.
爱那温情之火温暖了
∮ Love's own tender flames ∮
此刻的相逢
∮ Warm this meeting ∮
你将哼起那首轻柔的情歌
∮ And love's tender song you will sing ∮
可我美丽的鸟儿
∮ But fly away... ∮
我最近考虑了很多 妥协 这个词
I've been thinking a lot about the word "compromise."
一方面 她能上好学校
On one hand, good challenging school...
但另一方面
on the other...
寄养父母
foster people.
他们跟她一起看连续剧
They can watch sitcoms with her.
带她去橄榄花园
Take her to Olive Garden.
教她 不管不顾 这个词
Teach her to say "irregardless."
我想唯一的好处是
The only saving grace, I suppose,
她这样总比以前强
is she's better off than she was.
那么
Well...
再见 弗兰克
Goodbye, Frank.
喂
Hey...
别难过
come on.
我开车只需25分钟
I'm only 25 minutes away.
别把我留在这里
Please don't leave me here.
- 求你了 - 不
- Please. - No.
你要去
Look, you're going to
一所新学校 是好学校
a brand new school, a better school.
我不想去
I don't want to.
我想去我的烂学校
I want my crummy school.
- 你还有弗雷德 - 我不
- And you got Fred. - Please.
一个月可以回来一次
And once a month you can come back.
可以跟我和罗伯塔在一起
You can stay with me and Roberta.
我现在就要你和罗伯塔
I want you and Roberta now!
几年后 如果你愿意的话
And in a few years, if you want...
你可以回来 跟我住在一起
you can come back. You can live with me.
我想留在你那里
I wanna stay with you.
弗兰克 你跟我保证过的
Frank, you promised me.
- 别这样 - 你保证过的
- Come on. Don't do this. - You promised me.
我知道
I know.
求你了 弗兰克 你为什么要离开我
Please, Frank. Why are you leaving me?
因为这是法院判的 你是知道的
Because the court said I had to. You know this.
这事我们谈过多次
We've discussed this ad naus...
我们谈过的 拜托
We've discussed this. Come on.
- 拜托 - 不
- Come on, please. - No!
- 喂 玛丽 - 不
- Hey, Mary. - No!
喂 玛丽
Hey, Mary.
不 不
No! No!
孩子 这样吧
Sweetheart, you know what?
不
No!
开始谁都不会愿意
There's no easy way to do this.
但很快会好起来的 孩子
Not gonna be as long as you think, honey.
- 弗兰克 - 你会明白的
- Frank! - You're gonna see.
弗兰克
Frank!
别扔下我
Don't leave me!
- 我知道你难过 - 求你了
- I know this is hard. - Please!
不 放开我
No! Get your hands off of me!
- 弗兰克 求你了 - 我知道你难过
- Frank! Please! - I know it's hard.
- 回来 - 玛丽 我知道
- Come back! - Mary! I know.
不
No!
弗兰克
Frank!
别走
Don't go!
我需要你
I need you!
弗雷德需要你
Fred needs you!
你保证过的
You promised me!
不
No!
嗨
Hey, down there.
我不知道哪个错误更糟糕
I don't know which mistake is worse.
设计漏水的水泵
Designing a water pump that leaks...
还是把水泵放在够不到的地方
or putting it somewhere no human being can reach.
谁会设计知道会出故障的东西
How do you design something you know is gonna fail?
肯定是坏人或者笨蛋了
Gotta be devious or clueless, right?
我把玛丽带来几周之后
After the first few weeks, I knew...
就想给她找个真正的家庭
I had to find a real family for her.
我完全不懂抚养她
I was in way over my head.
我每天都对自己说
And every day, I'd say, "Today's the day...
今天说啥也要送她去儿童福利机构
"I'm takin' her to child services."
而她每一天都会做一件
And every day, she'd do something just...
那么可爱的事情
so unbelievably cool.
她性格形成的很快
Her little personality was exploding.
她风趣
She was funny.
她会生气 会开心 还会
And she was angry, and she was happy, and she was...
难过
sad.
还可爱
And was cute.
让我觉得好玩
Just so damn entertaining.
我就留下了她
And so I kept her.
倒不是为了她好
Not that that's in her best interest.
也不是因为我会抚养孩子
Not that I'm capable of raising a child.
如果我当时能留心注意到
A child that might still have a mother...
她妈妈需要我 她也就能有妈妈了
if I had taken the time to notice that she needed me.
到现在 六年半之后
And now, six and a half years later...
我终于把她送到了寄养家庭
I finally got her to the foster family,
你知道吗
and you know what?
那家人很好 她也喜欢
It was great. She loved it.
我本以为会是场噩梦
I thought it would be a nightmare...
抛弃和背叛
of abandonment and betrayal.
但结果却很成功
But, turns out it was a huge success.
我成了英雄
I'm a fucking hero.
- 弗兰克 - 不 邦妮
- Frank... - No, Bonnie.
我感谢你做的一切
I appreciate everything you've done.
别…
Just...
- 嗨 - 嗨 弗兰克
- Hey. - Hi, Frank.
家里出了点问题
We're having a little bit of a problem in there.
怎么了
What?
玛丽没事
Uh, Mary's fine...
但她有点情绪低落
but she's having a little bit of a meltdown.
是啊 让我劝劝她
Right. Let me talk to her.
不 等一下
No, hang on.
这样不好
That's not a good idea.
你来正是造成她情绪低落的原因
Your visit here is the reason for the meltdown.
什么
What?
她不想见你
She don't wanna see you.
对不起
I'm sorry, man.
这也不难理解
This is predictable.
她需要时间
You know, she needs time.
就让我跟她谈几分钟
Just give me five minutes with her.
如果让你进去
I let you inside...
就是背叛了她的信任
then we're gonna betray her trust
那样问题就更严重了
and we have an even bigger problem.
哦
Oh...
- 嗨 - 嗨 我能帮你什么
- Hi. - Hi! Can we help you?
是的 你们有一只叫弗雷德的橙色独眼猫吗
Yeah. Do you have a one-eyed orange cat named Fred?
我们有一只独眼猫
We have a one-eyed cat,
但我不知道它的名字
but I don't know what his name is.
在哪儿
Where?
不知道 今天是它的最后一天了
I don't know. Today was his last day.
喂 你不能去后面
Hey, you can't go back there.
喂
Hey.
喂喂 你到后面干什么
Whoa, whoa, whoa, what are you doing back here?
我说过他不能来
I told him he couldn't.
嗨 弗雷德
Hey, Fred.
是谁把猫送来的
Who brought this cat in?
是个男人 他说他对猫过敏
Some guy. He said it was an allergy issue.
伊芙琳
Evelyn.
- 弗兰克 - 伊芙琳在哪儿
- Frank! - Where's Evelyn?
伊芙琳 你是说你母亲
Evelyn? You mean your mother?
- 是的 - 凯文
- Yes. - Kevin.
伊芙琳在客房里
Evelyn is in the guest house.
听着 我很抱歉
Yeah, listen. I'm sorry, man.
弗兰克 听我说
Frank, let me tell you,
她请了很好的家教
she was so helpful with the tutors.
- 玛丽很孤僻 - 喂
- Mary was so distant. - Hey!
我们知道你的情况
Look, we know what you're up against.
你想回到从前吗
Do you want your life back?
不想的话就回去
Go back inside.
你来干什么
What are you doing here?
来 玛丽 我们回家
Come on, Mary. We're goin' home.
- 不 - 你是擅闯私宅
- No. - You're trespassing!
你需要看看这个
You need to look at this.
我们走 玛丽
Let's go, Mary.
- 我们走 - 不
- Let's move. Come on. - No!
- 喂 玛丽 - 玛丽
- Hey! Mary. - Mary!
玛丽
Mary!
没事 我去追她
It's okay. I got her.
有种你试试
Think again, lady.
玛丽
Mary!
玛丽 喂 站住
Mary! Hey, stop it.
不 放开我
No! Let me go!
不
No!
- 不 - 住手 玛丽
- No! No! - Stop, Mary!
- 住手 - 不
- Stop. Stop. - No!
- 过来 - 你骗了我
- Come here. - You lied to me!
我知道
I know!
- 不 不 - 住手 住手
- No! No! - Stop! Stop, stop!
对不起
I'm sorry.
我犯了个错误 我很抱歉
I made a mistake. I'm so sorry.
你保证过的
You promised me.
我知道
I know.
你保证过的
You promised.
我知道 对不起
I know. I'm sorry.
你说过不会离开我的
You said you wouldn't leave me.
我犯了个错误
I made a mistake.
对不起
I'm sorry.
我那时好难过
I was so sad!
我想你
I missed you.
我也想你
I missed you, too.
他们把弗雷德送走了
They took Fred.
不 没事的
No. It's okay.
- 我找到它了 它就在家里 - 什么
- I got him. He's home. - What?
它现在就在家里 我找到它了
He's at the apartment right now. I got him.
真的吗
For real?
是的 它正在踢它的乒乓球呢
Yeah. He's home kicking around his ping pong ball.
你为什么把我留在这里
Why did you leave me there?
因为我觉得我抚养不好你
Because I thought I was bad for you.
但我后来明白
And then it dawned on me.
既然玛丽成了这么棒
If Mary is this amazing...
聪明 可爱的女孩
smart, sweet human being...
那说明我肯定做对了什么
then I must be doing something right.
你笑了
You're smiling.
罗伯特
Roberta!
孩子
Oh, baby.
你竟然搞这一出
Of all the stunts you could pull.
- 她们要去哪儿 - 不去哪儿
- Where are they going? - Nowhere.
还不到时候
Not yet.
你们俩出去
You two, out!
- 这是什么 - 你想知道
- What is this? - Do you want to know...
黛安完成后怎么对我说的吗
how Diane told me she finished?
这是什么昧着良心的谎言
What is this unconscionable lie?
我走进她家
I walked into her apartment
她坐在地板上
and she was sitting on the floor...
怀里抱着孩子
with that baby in her arms
你知道她怎么对我说的吗
and you know what she said to me?
承认吧 这是你编出来的
Admit it. You made this up.
- 她说 我现在该怎么办 - 不
- She said, "What do I do now?" - No.
这不是完整的证明
It is not a completed proof...
- 是 - 这不是 不可能
- It is. - No! It isn't! It can't be.
伊芙琳 别说了
Evelyn, stop!
我要带走玛丽 抚养她
I'm taking Mary and I'm raising her
以我认为黛安所希望的方式
how I believe Diane would've wanted.
- 这由不得你 - 我知道…
- We'll see about that later. - I realize...
她不是普通人
she's not normal.
但既然爱因斯坦能骑自行车 那么她也能
But if Einstein can ride a bike, so can she.
就算是黛安没告诉我 尽管这很荒唐
Let's just say Diane didn't tell me, which is nonsense...
这毕竟是千年难题
it's a Millennium Problem.
她肯定会发表出来
She would have shared it with the world.
这是你露馅的地方
That's where your charade falls apart.
如果她完成了证明
If she had completed the proof,
她肯定会发表
she would have published it.
黛安对我说的很清楚
Diane instructed me very clearly.
只能在死后发表
That I was only to publish it postmortem.
她四年前就死了
She died six years ago.
她说的不是在她死后
It wasn't her death she was talking about.
我试图劝过她
I tried to talk her out of it.
但你知道黛安的脾气
But you know how Diane could be
下定决心就没人劝得动
when she made her mind up about something.
我给麻省理工打过电话
I called MIT.
尚克兰很期待
Shankland's out of his mind
能和你一起发表它
about the possibility of publishing it with you.
他在等你的电话
He's waiting for your call.
你接下来几年会忙着
You're gonna be spending the next few years of your life...
维护它
defending it.
不会有时间照料她
You won't have time for her.
如果我拒绝呢
What if I say no?
那就继续按她的遗愿
Back to Plan A.
等我死后再发表
Wait for me to die?
我知道黛安很倔强
I know Diane was hard.
我知道她生你的气
I know she was angry.
但这也带来了好的一面 伊芙琳
But something really good came out of this, Evelyn.
她现在需要你
She needs you now.
你是这项工作的不二人选
You're the best woman for the job.
接受了吧
Take it.
可是黛安并不想把它给我
It doesn't seem as though Diane wanted me to have it.
黛安考虑事情不够周全
Diane didn't always think things through.
我先出去了
I'll be outside.
你决定之后告诉我一声
Let me know what you wanna do.
这里是
You've reached
麻省理工学院数学系
the Department of Mathematics at MIT.
如果你知道对方分机号码
If you know your party's extension,
请直接拨打
you may dial it at any time.
如果你想联系接线员
If you wish to speak to an operator...
请不要挂断
please stay on the line
会很快有人接听你的电话
and someone will be with you as soon as possible.
下午好 麻省理工数学系
Good afternoon, MIT Mathematics,
你要找哪位
how may I direct your call?
喂 抱歉 我听不清你
Hello? I'm sorry. I can't hear you very well.
不
No! No.
好的 听到你了
Yeah. There you are.
我能帮你什么吗
Yeah, can I help you?
是的
Uh, yes.
尚克兰博士
Doctor Shankland.
对不起 我听不清
I'm really sorry. I can't hear you.
你能大点声吗
Could you speak up, please?
喂
Hello?
我是伊芙琳阿德勒
Evelyn Adler...
我找西摩尚克兰
for Seymore Shankland, please.
你们要注意的是
And what I want you to notice,
当通过N计算P时
is that when you compute P of N...
N等于4模除5
for N congruent to four mod five...
答案是5的倍数
the answer is a multiple of five.
最早发现这一点的人
So, the first person to notice this
是斯里尼瓦瑟拉马努金
was Srinivasa Ramanujan.
在20世纪初
In the beginning of the 20th century...
他证明了所有全等于
he proved that it was the case for all...
4模除5的数字都是如此
numbers congruent to four mod five.
他证明了P等于5的倍数加4
So, he proved that P of five N plus four...
等于0模除7
is congruent to zero mod seven...
P等于11的倍数加6
and that P of eleven N plus six
全等于0模除11
is congruent to zero mod eleven.
还好吗
Good?
你开车慢死了
You drive like an old lady.
这里是佛罗里达 我是入乡随俗
It's Florida. I'm blending in.
在学校怎么样
How was school?
挺有趣的
Hmm, fun.
不是普通学校那种有趣
Not like regular school fun...
但也不错
but interesting.
这是什么书
What is this book?
方法论 勒内笛卡尔所著
Discourse on Method. René Descartes.
讲什么的
What's it about?
存在
Existence.
Existence?
是的 我思故我在
Yup. "I think, therefore I am."
你当然在
Well, of course you are.
这很明显
That's obvious.
我思弗雷德 故我在
I think about Fred, therefore, I am.
Cogito ergo Fred?
它是只公猫 是雄性
He's a dude and he's a guy.
只有一只眼
And he only has one eye.
弗雷德 弗雷德
Fred, Fred, Fred!
Freddy, Fred, Fred!
好了 到了
All right, here we are.
喂 等停车后再开门
Hey! Wait till I come to a stop.
那就快停车啊
Then come to a stop already!